What did you experience on October 7?
I've been in the same room with my wife Nira,
my daughter Dor and her child Rif,
he was 2 years old.
And in the same time her oldest one was with the other
grandmother and father.
They are living in the kibbutz
in a more dangerous place.
It's Gefen, then he was 4 years old,
and his father,
my son in law,
Dekel, wasn't in the same unit of the kibbuz.
He was going outside,
outside,
to protect us.
I was in charge in the safe room about the boy,
about his mother,
and two dogs that we have in the safe room.
My wife Nira,
years ago she was in the army.
So we say about her that
"You can take her out of the army,"
"but you can not take the army out of her"
So she was
She collected all the SOS messages
from the people and
sent it to the army.
She sent them
the location from WhatsApp.
The army, she knew for every commander
in the part of the kibbutz where he is
and she sent them to the people,
to help people.
And when she got out at
Sunday,
2:30 am, we got out,
she decided to to stay in the kibbutz.
We were going to to Kibbutz Shefayim,
and she decided to stay in the kibbutz,
to help the soldiers.
Until Monday they took (evacuated)
the alive people and after that
for two and a half more days
they had to identify our friends,
the dead ones. The dead people.
She identified
most of the people who got killed here.
And after that she came
to Shefayim, came back to me.
I don't know how to describe it,
of course, but not in English.
But we tried to rebuild our life again.
It was...
until now
It's very
very hard to do it,
because of Gali and Ziv (Berman),
because we don't have a house.
We are refugees in our country.
And because so many people
are not with us now.
They are gone and it's hard to
to rebuild the life, but we're trying
I hope that soon we'll be able
to come (back) to Kfar Aza.
It will take a year or something,
but I hope that we will.